Guide to the New Day Films Archive, 1969-2018 RL.10180
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Digital Films Collection, 1971-2018; 12 Terabytes 214 digital files
  - Goldsmith, Rick; Ginzberg, Abby
    - Everyday Heroes, 2001; 120 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_EverydayHeroes_2hr.mp4)
      Everyday Heroes takes a behind-the-headlines look at a diverse group of young adults who give a year of their lives through a San Francisco area AmeriCorps program to tutor and mentor needy kids. Despite their good intentions, they are confronted by a host of obstacles, including a racial divide that threatens to thwart their efforts. While documenting a year both turbulent and exhilarating, the film reveals the hopes and dreams, successes and setbacks of a group of individuals--potentially tomorrow's leaders-- searching for their place in the world and trying, against odds, to make a difference. Produced by Abby Ginzberg, Rick Goldsmith.
    - Everyday Heroes, 2001; 59 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0044_u, Video-file GoldsmithRick_EverydayHeroes_59mins.mp4)
  - Gossels, Lisa
    - My So Called Enemy, 2010; 89 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0045_u, Video-file GosselsLisa_MySoCalledEnemy.mp4)
      Spanning seven years, "My So-Called Enemy" follows six Palestinian and Israeli teenage girls committed to justice and mutual understanding after participating in a cross-cultural women's leadership program in the U.S. called Building Bridges for Peace. This heart and mind-opening film, from Emmy Award-winning director Lisa Gossels (The Children of Chabannes), documents how the young women's transformative experience of knowing their "enemies" as human beings meets with the realities of their lives back home in the Middle East. Through the coming-of-age narratives of Adi, Gal, Hanin, Inas, Rawan and Rezan, audiences see how creating relationships across personal, political, cultural, religious and geographic borders are first steps towards resolving conflict. "My So-Called Enemy" presents the complexities of the Israeli/Palestinian conflict through a human lens, and the possibility and hope that come from listening to each others stories. Produced by Produced by Lisa Gossels and Eden Wurmfeld, Co-Producer Justin Schein.
  - Green, Cheryl
    - Who Am I To Stop It, 2016; 86 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0046_u, Video-file GreenCheryl_WhoAmIToStopIt.mp4)
      Three everyday people with traumatic brain injury disabilities use arts to reconnect to a sense of identity, self-pride, and community and to assert their agency and self-advocacy. This feature-length documentary centers the artists' narratives with compassion and honesty, creating complex portraits that go beyond the medical aspects of brain injury that typically dominate educational media on the topic.
      This film contains mature themes and adult language. Audio Description available on DVD and New Day Streaming.
  - Herold, Kara
    - Bachelorette 34, 2009; 30 min (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0047_u, Video-file HeroldKara_Bachelorette34.mp4)
      Kara's mother is obsessed with getting her daughter married. Kara, a single artist and filmmaker in San Francisco, has her doubts. Through the microcosm of her often hilarious interactions with her mom, KaraHerold's Bachelorette, 34 examines the pressure society puts on women to find "Mr. Right." Produced by Kara Herold.
  - Herring, Christie
    - The Campaign, 2013; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0048_u, Video-file HerringChristie_TheCampaign_ProRes_STEREO.mp4)
      THE CAMPAIGN follows the people behind California's historic No-on-8 campaign to defend same-sex marriage through exclusive behind the scenes footage, interwoven with the national history of same-sex relationship recognition since the 1950s.
  - Hershfield, Joanne
    - The Gillian Film, 2006; 44 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0049_u, Video-file HershfieldJoanne_TheGillianFilm.mp4)
      The Gillian Film is a moving portrait of an exceptional young woman who works at a local veterinary clinic, rides horses, takes dance classes, and is developmentally disabled. The film shares the difficulties and joys of both raising and being a person whose abilities are in constant and productive tension with her distinctive thought styles and cognitive capacities. Ultimately, however, through an examination of one life defined a different, The Gillian Film explores how we might transform our understanding of the meaning and worth of people with developmental disabilities. Produced by Joanne Hershfield.
    - Men Are Human Women Are Buffalo, 2008; 29 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0049_u, Video-file HershfieldJoanne_MenAreHumanWomenAreBuffalo.mp4)
      A country that is promoted to western tourists as a fairytale land of beautiful beaches, pristine countryside, cheap vacations, and a thriving sex trade industry, Thailand is also one of the developing countries with the highest incidence of violence against women. Approximately 44 percent of women in Thailand have indicated that they have suffered sexual, physical, and emotional abuse by a partner or a stranger. While these five stories are culturally specific, their commonality with the experiences of other women will provoke productive discussions about incidence of violence against women around the world. Produced by Joanne Hershfield.
    - These Are Our Children, 2010; 55 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0049_u, Video-file HershfieldJoanne_TheseAreOurChildren.mp4)
      These Are Our Children reveals how the devastating effects of poverty, HIV/AIDs, and violence on Kenyan children are successfully being reduced through grassroots interventions. Over 300,000 children live on the streets Nairobi, stealing, begging, and prostituting themselves for food and money and more than one million children in Kenya have been affected by the HIV-AIDs crisis. Yet, through hope and hard work, we learn from the children and the adults they work with that schools and grass-root organizations are creating a future in which all children can realize their dreams to be teachers, pilots, doctors, generals, and world-famous soccer players. Produced by Joanne Hershfield.
    - Mama C Urban Warrior In The African Bush, 2012; 53 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0049_u, Video-file HershfieldJoanne_MamaCUrbanWarriorInTheAfricanBush.mp4)
      A former member of the Kansas City Black Panther Party, Mama C, a poet, musician, artist, and community activist, has lived for over forty years as an "urban warrior in the African Bush"; in the Tanzanian village of Imbaseni. As she writes in one of her published poems: "in my freshly-landed, just-got-off-the-boat enthusiasm of living in Africa, I tried to blend, to melt, homogenize, disappear, erase, the essence of what made me who I am, an African, who grew up in and was molded by the 'hoods' of America, and I almost lost myself." Produced by Joanne Hershfield.
  - Hessman, Robin
    - My Perestroika, 2010; 87 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0050_u, Video-file HessmanRobin_MyPerestroika.mp4)
      When the USSR broke apart in 1991, a generation of young people faced a new realm of possibilities. An intimate epic about the extraordinary lives of this last Soviet generation, Robin Hessman's feature documentary tells the stories of five Moscow schoolmates who were brought up behind the Iron Curtain, witnessed the joy and confusion of Glasnost, and reached adulthood just as the world changed around them. Through candid first-person testimony, revealing verité footage, and vintage home movies from her subjects, Hessman, who spent many years living in Moscow, reveals a Russia rarely ever seen on film, where people are frank about their lives and forthcoming about their country. Engaging, funny, and positively inspiring, in My Perestroika politics is personal, honesty overshadows ideology, and history progresses one day, one life at a time. Produced by Rachel Wexler, Robin Hessman.
  - Hill, Isabel
    - Made In Brooklyn, 1993; 55 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0051_u, Video-file HillIsabel_MadeInBrooklyn.mp4)
      The compelling stories of factories that flourish in Brooklyn, NY, challenge the notion that manufacturing is dead in America. Workers reveal how their jobs bring not only regular pay checks, but meaningful relationships, enhanced self-esteem, and pride in themselves and their products. Made in Brooklyn has lessons about the economy for the entire nation. Produced by Isabel Hill.
    - Brooklyn Matters, 2007; 60 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0051_u, Video-file HillIsabel_BrooklynMatters.mp4)
      Brooklyn Matters is a riveting look at how big real estate, politics, community voices, and the desperate need for jobs and housing clash in one of the largest development proposals in the history of New York City. The film poses vital, timely questions that are relevant to cities across the country: What is the proper use of eminent domain? What role does environmental and economic justice play in government-sponsored projects? Who represents the community? Should traffic-intensive projects be approved without mandatory mitigation measures? Should taxpayer money go to acquire private property for a sports area? What and who determines if an area is "blighted?" Does the public have a right to know about the use of public finances in large-scale real estate projects? Brooklyn Matters brings a depth of expert commentary to the debate and introduces many important community voices that have struggled to be heard on this project. This film's exploration of the risks that come with a concentration of power is important for anyone concerned with who has a voice and who has a vote in shaping the future of our cities. Produced by Isabel Hill.
    - Blind Faith, 2016; 53 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0051_u, Video-file HillIsabel_BlindFaith.mp4)
      Blind Faith follows the stirring personal journey, both intimate and universal, of a man coming to terms with his disability and struggling with the roles of father, husband, and successful entrepreneur, breaking through the myths of blindness and broadening our understanding of the complex hidden realities facing the blind community.
  - Huang, Kathy
    - Tales Of The Waria, 2011; 56 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0052_u, Video-file HuangKathy_TalesOfTheWaria.mp4)
      Indonesia is home to the world's largest Muslim population. It is also home to the "warias," a community of biological men who live openly as women. In this eye-opening PBS documentary, four warias search for romance and intimacy. They encounter a host of obstacles-- family pressures, economic burdens, aging-- but strive to stay true to themselves and to find lasting companionship. Shot over three years with the local queer community serving as story consultants and film crew members, the film provides an unprecedented look into topics rarely discussed in Western media: Indonesia, Islamic culture, and the daily life and struggles of transgender communities around the world. Produced by Kathy Huang.
  - Jennings, Katie
    - The Red Pines, 2003; 12 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0053_u, Video-file JenningsKatie_TheRedPines.mp4)
      The Red Pines, a short film for university and K-12 classrooms, explores the Japanese American community on Puget Sound's Bainbridge Island. It shows the cultural forces that enabled many of its members to return and rebuild their lives after exile and incarceration by their own government during World War II.
    - Teachings Tree People, 2006; 58 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0053_u, Video-file JenningsKatie_TeachingsTreePeople.mp4)
      Bruce Miller is a Skokomish spiritual leader who nourished a renaissance of art and culture in the Pacific Northwest and beyond. He's a master of Skokomish basketry, weaving and cedar-mat making, oral history and storytelling. Knowledgeable in topics as diverse as medicinal herbs and ceremonial protocol, Bruce is a Renaissance man and a leader in the movement to bring back native art and culture in the Northwest and beyond. The National Endowment for the Arts honored him with the National Heritage Fellowship for this work. He's also known as "uncle" to the many apprentices who discover their own dormant strengths as they learn to practice cultural traditions at his side.Teachings of the Tree People chronicles Bruce's childhood on the Skokomish reservation; his young adulthood in college, in war, and with a national theater company; and his return home to lead a cultural renaissance. With the help of apprentices, he strips tree bark and annoints it with natural dyes, grows and prepares medicines, weaves with wool and cedar, and prepares wild foods for a community Ceremony of First Foods.Four is an important number in Indian country. It's the number of the seasons and the number of cardinal directions. It's also the number of times one is expected to listen to a story to really begin to hear it. Bruce tells his own bittersweet tale of cultural knowledge in four chapters that grow, branch, interconnect and reach toward the sky. Produced by Katie Jennings.
  - Jensen, Christian
    - White Earth, 2014; 19 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0054_u, Video-file JensenChristian_WhiteEarth.mp4)
      "White Earh is an Oscar® Nominated portrait of an oil boom through a child's eyes. Thousands of souls flock to America's Northern Plains seeking work in the oil fields. Three children and an immigrant mother brave a cruel winter and reflect on the challenges and opportunities of life in the nation's biggest oil rush. Produced by J. Christian Jensen.
  - Kaneko, Ann
    - Against The Grain, 2008; 65 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0055_u, Video-file KanekoAnn_AgainstTheGrain.mp4)
      In 1989, Alfredo Marquéz used an image of Mao in an artwork. He was sentenced to 20 years in prison. For every artist, the need to create and be heard is as basic as food and shelter. But what happens when you live in a country where the state clamps down on free thinkers, forcing artists to censor themselves? Four Peruvian visual artists, including Marquéz, defy this tyranny through their work and ignite change, challenging ordinary people to speak out. Spanning two decades of corrupt governments and inept leaders, this film tells the story of these inspiring artists.
  - Kantayya, Shalini
    - Catching The Sun, 2016; 73 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0056_u, Video-file KantayyaShalini_CatchingTheSun.mp4)
      Over the course of a solar jobs training program, Catching the Sun follows the hope and heartbreak of unemployed American workers seeking jobs in the solar industry. With countries like China investing in innovative technologies and capitalizing on this trillion-dollar opportunity, Catching the Sun tells the story of the global energy transition from the perspective of workers and entrepreneurs building solutions to income inequality and climate change with their own hands. Their successes and failures speak to one of the biggest questions of our time: will the U.S. actually be able to build a clean energy economy?
  - Khan, Sofian
    - Gaucho Del Norte, 57 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0057_u, Video-file KhanSofian_GauchoDelNorte.mp4)
      Far from his family in Chile, sheepherder Eraldo Pacheco must endure harsh conditions and loneliness in the high desert and isolated mountain pastures of the American west as he strives for a better life for his family. This immersive documentary offers a lyrical meditation on what it means to be an immigrant.
  - Kondo, Alan
    - …I Told You So, 1974; 18 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0091_u, Video-file KondoAlan_IToldYouSo_VC.mp4)
      …I Told You So weaves scenes of Japanese American poet and professor Lawson Inada's life with his writings. Part of New Day's Visual Communications Collection.
  - Kubo, Duane
    - City City, 1974; 12 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0092_u, Video-file KuboDuane_CityCity_VC.mp4)
      The vibrancy of the City of Los Angeles is expressed by an intricate interweaving of optical print effects and an eclectic soundtrack. This experimental narrative piece offers an abstract view of a contemporary city and the people who inhabit it. Part of New Day's Visual Communications Collection.
    - Cruisin J-Town, 1975; 24 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0092_u, Video-file KuboDuane_CruisinJTown_VC.mp4)
      Cruisin' J-Town celebrates the music and influences of contemporary Asian American culture on Dan Kuramoto, June Okida Kuramoto, and Johnny Mori — three musicians who make up the core of the jazz fusion band Hiroshima. Part of New Day's Visual Communications Collection.
  - Lagarde, Charlotte
    - Heart of Sea, 2002; 54 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0058_u, Video-file CharlotteLagarde_HeartofSea.mp4)
      Hailed as "remarkable" by Teacher Librarian and "enthusiastically recommended" by Video Librarian, Heart of the Sea is a breathtaking portrait of surf legend Rell "Kapolioka'ehukai" Sunn, founding member of the Women's Professional Surfing Association and beloved breast cancer activist. With exhilarating water scenes and captivating archival footage of surf culture, Heart of the Sea is an important look at Hawaii's integral part of America's rich cultural heritage.
  - Lau, Pat; Miller, Don
    - To Be Me: Tony Quon, 1973; 10 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0093_u, Video-file LauPat_MillerDon_ToBeMeTonyQuon_VC.mp4)
      Tony, an active ten-year-old Chinese immigrant, describes adjusting to an American school. Tony describes his first impressions of "strange new classrooms", as the film journeys with him through Los Angeles. Part of New Day's Visual Communications Collection.
  - Leland, Andrea
    - The Long Road Home, 1993; 30 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0059_u, Video-file LelandAndrea_TheLongRoadHome.mp4)
      During the 1980's, the CIA backed the Guatemalan government's efforts to destroy the resistance movement that was growing among the indigenous Maya peoples. Human rights organizations around the world condemned the army's "scorch and burn" policy, whereby the government backed militia razed over indigenous 200 villages along the Mexican / Guatemalan border in their attempts to crush the guerillas. Thousands of Maya fled across the border into Mexico seeking refuge and to save their lives.
    - The Garifuna Journey, 1998; 46 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0059_u, Video-file LelandAndrea_TheGarifunaJourney.mp4)
      A first voice testimony celebrating the resiliency of the Garifuna people and their traditions. Shot entirely in Belize, the filmmakers worked closely with Garifuna tradition bearers, anthropologists and cultural activists during the research, scripting, production and editing phases of this project. The documentary resulting from this "outsider and insider" collaboration is the first of its kind, one that captures the triumph of spirit of the Garifuna people. Descendants of African and Carib-Indian ancestors, the Garifuna fought to maintain their homeland and resisted slavery. For this love of freedom, they were exiled by the British in 1797. Despite exile and subsequent Diaspora, their traditional culture survives today. It is a little known story that deserves its place in the annals of the African Diaspora. In authentic Garifuna voices, this documentary presents the history, the language, food, music, dance and spirituality of the Garifuna culture. It is a celebratory documentary, with engaging scenes of fishing, cooking, dancing, cassava preparation, thatching a temple, spiritual ritual, ritual music and dance all demonstrating the Garifuna link to the Carib-African past. Produced by Andrea E. Leland & Kathy Berger.
    - Jamesie King of Scratch, 2006; 70 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0059_u, Video-file LelandAndrea_JamesieKingofScratch.mp4)
      Award-winning filmmaker Andrea E. Leland collaborated with James Brewster to create a 70-minute documentary and archiving project. The result of their collaboration is a spirited musical journey to the Caribbean focusing on Scratch band music (also known as Quelbe), an indigenous, grass-roots form of folk music from the Virgin Islands that was recently declared the "official" music of the Virgin Islands. 79-year old James Brewster, the central character of this documentary, is an uncompromising, humorous, and provocative musician known for his playful compositions and lively performances and is the legendary "King of Scratch".This engaging documentary includes performances by Jamesie and the All-Stars at a St. Croix nightclub; an agricultural fair on St. Croix; the World Music Festival and the Old Town School of Folk Music in Chicago; the Lotus Music Festival in Bloomington, Indiana; jamming with his friends; and performing and teaching in Denmark. Interspersed with these performances is more intimate footage of Jamesie talking with other musicians about the historical significance of the music and explaining how he came to create some of his songs and footage at his home revealing his more personal side. The documentary celebrates Scratch band music and one of it's most legendary performers. It provides a unique opportunity to view up close and personal the US Virgin Islands' deep-rooted musical tradition. Produced by Andea Leland.
    - Yurumein, 2014; 50 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0059_u, Video-file LelandAndrea_Yurumein.mp4)
      YURUMEIN (your-o-main) is an important UNTOLD STORY of Carib/Garifuna resistance against slavery that deserves its place in the annals of the African Diaspora. The film recounts the painful past of the Caribs on St Vincent and the extermination of scores of their ancestors at the hands of the British, while building an intimate portrait of Garifuna culture in-transition today. We are given firsthand accounts from both Carib descendants who remain on the island of St Vincent and voices of returning descendants whose ancestors were exiled to Central America—where Garifuna traditional culture was able to survive and flourish.When members of the Diaspora are first reunited and make a collective pilgrimage to the sacred site of Balliceaux (where the genocide occurred) the film reveals the beginnings of a movement among Garifuna people to revitalize traditional language, music, dance, and ritual. This scene features the Garifuna National Folkloric Ballet of Honduras. As Garifuna from around the world come together to remember and celebrate the lives and resilience of their shared ancestors, they also begin to discover possibility and hope for the future of Garifuna culture and a greater worldwide community. The film includes original music by Garifuna artists: Andy Palacio and Rhodel Castillo. Additional music by Abuza from St. Vincent. Original artwork by Garifuna artist Greg Palacio. Produced by Andrea E. Leland.
  - Li, Yoyo
    - Under The Same Sky, 2017; 19 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0061_u, Video-file LiYoyo_UnderTheSameSky.mp4)
      During the Chinese government's national campaign on "equal" education, discover the different reality of a city versus a countryside boy as they both go to school.
  - Lieff, Judy
    - Deaf Jam, 2010; 70 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0060_u, Video-file LieffJudy_DeafJam.mp4)
      "Poetry, friendship and respect transcend politics; delightful and endearing, utilizing upbeat music and clever graphics, Deaf Jam immerses us in the richness and complexity of deaf culture and gives us a unique perspective into a world so vibrant, so diverse, it may forever change the way we see the non-hearing." Produced by Judy Lieff.
  - Liem, Deann Borshay
    - First Person Plural, 2000; 60 minutes (Digital-materials RL10180-SET-0062_u, Video-file BorshayLiemDeann_FirstPersonPlural.mp4)